Manfred A. Carter Papers
Manfred A. Carter Papers
1905-1965
Carter, Manfred Amos.
18 linear ft.
Papers of the American clergyman, author, poet. Biographical and family material, correspondence, memorabilia, including cartoons, church bulletins, financial documents, original drawings, photographs, school and seminary papers, and scrapbooks. Writings include an inventory of prose works, a reviews scrapbook, articles, editorials, fiction, lyrics, and manuscript poems arranged chronologically in notebooks, dated pre-1940-1961. Also included are a large collection of chronologically arranged sermons as well as children's sermons. There are also a number of essays arranged in titled notebooks.
148889
Biographical History
Manfred Amos Carter (1897-1971) was a Methodist minister who received his education at Wesleyan University and Boston University. He was also a published poet and author whose work appeared in religious periodicals, various newspapers and small poetry magazines.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Manfred A. Carter Papers consists of biographical and family material, correspondence, memorabilia, and writings.
Biographical and family material includes miscellaneous material about Carter and his family. Family correspondence is interfiled in Correspondence, which includes both incoming and outgoing.
Photographs, school and seminary papers, financial documents, a scrapbook, and miscellaneous other items comprise Memorabilia
The bulk of the collection is Carter's Writings, in both manuscript and published forms. This includes articles, editorials, fiction, lyrics, poetry, sermons, and speeches, as well as several notebooks containing manuscripts of various pieces.
Arrangement of the Collection
Within each series material is arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Church and clergy; Carter, Manfred Amos -- Archives.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Clergy -- United States.; Clergy as authors.; Clergy, Writings of.; Poets, American -- 20th century.; Sermons, American.; Correspondence.; Editorials.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scrapbooks.; Sermons.; Authors.; Clergy.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical and family material
  - Miscellaneous (non-correspondence), Family correspondence is interfiled in Correspondence section. (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 13 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 12 folders (Box 5)
- Memorabilia
  - Artwork
    - Cartoons
      - Scrapbooks, 2 items (Box 6)
      - Tearsheets (Box 6)
    - Original drawings (Box 6)
    - Painting inventories (Box 6)
  - Church bulletins, 2 folders and 2 scrapbooks (Box 7)
  - Financial documents (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 2 folders and 1 scrapbook (Box 8)
  - School and seminary papers, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook (general) (Box 8)
  - Miscellanea (Box 8)
- Writings (in manuscript)
  - Inventory of prose works (Box 9)
  - Reviews scrapbook (Box 9)
  - Articles (some miscellaneous manuscripts are interfiled), 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Articles, 8 folders (Box 10)
  - Articles, 9 folders (Box 11)
  - Editorials (Box 12)
  - Fiction, 4 scrapbooks of short fiction (Box 12)
  - Fiction: arranged by Carter into Adventure, Crime, Fantasy, Humor, 4 scrapbooks (Box 13)
  - Fiction: arranged by Carter into Love (2), Quality, Western, Miscellaneous, 5 scrapbooks (Box 14)
  - Lyrics (Box 14)
  - Poetry
    - Poetry inventories, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Manuscripts, 10 folders (Box 15)
    - Notebooks, chronologically arranged by Carter
      - 1940 and before (Box 16)
      - 1941-1942 (Box 16)
      - 1943-1946 (Box 16)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 17)
      - 1949-1951 (Box 17)
      - 1952-1954 (Box 17)
      - 1955-1957 (Box 18)
      - 1958-1961 (Box 18)
      - Undated, 2 notebooks (Box 19)
  - Sermons
    - Notebooks, 2 notebooks (Box 19)
    - Sermons in Guilford (Box 19)
    - Children's sermons (Box 19)
    - Sermons (chronological sequence), 9 folders (Box 20)
    - Sermons (chronological sequence), 7 folders (Box 21)
    - Sermons (chronological sequence), 11 folders (Box 22)
    - Sermons (chronological sequence), 6 folders (Box 23)
    - Sermons (numerical sequence), 1-120, 5 folders (Box 23)
    - Sermons (numerical sequence), 121-260, 6 folders (Box 24)
    - Selected sermons (Box 24)
  - Talks, 9 folders (Box 25)
  - Titled notebook manuscripts, as arranged by Carter
    - "Christian Sensitivity" (Box 26)
    - "Coyotes" (Box 26)
    - "Earth Windows" (Box 26)
    - "The House of Art" (Box 27)
    - "How ... the Educated" (Box 27)
    - "Learning from Death" (Box 27)
    - "Like a Tree Planted" (Box 27)
    - "Moving Morals" (Box 28)
    - "Paul Brown's Life" (Box 28)
    - "Roots of Crime" (Box 28)
    - "Selected Citizens" (Box 28)
    - "Spring Minds for Thoughtful Ministers" (Box 29)
    - "Starters 1-4" (Box 29)
    - "Starters 5-6" (Box 29)
    - "Starters 6" (Box 29)
    - "Starters 7-12" (Box 29)
    - "Substance Poetry" (Box 30)
    - "Time Windows" (Box 30)
    - "The Unquiet Heart" (Box 30)
  - Unidentified manuscript notes (Box 30)
- Writings (as published)
  - A-Z, alphabetical by title (Box 31)
  - Clippings notebook of published poetry before 1962 (Box 32)
  - Clippings of published prose, 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Journal contributions (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 32)